Guide to the Andrew Davis Collection on Jedwabne, Poland
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Andrew Davis collection on Jedwabne, Poland
1981-2001
MS 1910
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1
(1 box)
This collection consists of monographs, clippings, pamphlets, e-mail correspondence and other materials related to the city of Jedwabne, Poland, the murder of the town's Jews in July 1941, and Jewish-Polish relations in general. Of particular interest are the materials related to a memorial ceremony on July 10, 2001, honoring the murdered Jews of Jedwabne.
Davis, Andrew
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Received by the Fortunoff Video Archive for Holocaust Testimonies from Andrew Davis, 2001, and transferred to Manuscripts and Archives, 2008.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Andrew Davis's interest in the city of Jedwabne, Poland, stems from familial ties to the town. His grandfather emigrated to the United States from Jedwabne in 1888. However, the town is most infamous for a massacre of its Jews committed by Polish civilians in July 1941. This crime was the subject of the book Neighbors, by Jan Gross. Davis has also engaged in the study of this massacre, and over several years has collected research materials related to Jedwabne. In July 2001, Davis was invited to attend a ceremony commemorating the 60th anniversary of the massacre in Jedwabne.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of monographs, clippings, pamphlets, e-mail correspondence and other materials related to the city of Jedwabne, Poland, the murder of the town's Jews in July 1941, and Jewish-Polish relations in general. Of particular interest are the materials related to a memorial ceremony on July 10, 2001, honoring the murdered Jews of Jedwabne.
Arrangement
The collection is organized as received from the collector.
Massacres -- Jews; Jedwabne (Poland); Davis, Andrew
- Monographs
  Scope and Contents
  Includes photocopies from several historical works that mention Jedwabne. For bibliographic records for each monograph, consult Orbis, the Yale University Library's online catalog.
  - Baka, Igor. Zidovsky tabor v Novakoch, 1941-1944, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    In Slovak.
  - Thou Shalt Not Kill: Poles on Jedwabne, contributors Jacek Borkowicz et al.; text revised and edited by William Brand; introduction by Israel Gutman, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Why Auschwitz? Why Kolyma? Why Kosovo?: A Discussion about the History, Christian Culture Foundation "ZNAK," The Polish Council of Christians and Jews, and Chancellery of the Prime Minister of the Republic of Poland, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Niekrasz, Lech Z. Operacja "Jedwabne": Mity i Fakty = Operation "Jedwabne": Myths and Facts, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    In Polish, with a summary in English.
  - Nowak, Jerzy Robert. Sto klamstw J.T. Grossa o Jedwabnem i zydowskich sasiadach, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    In Polish.
  - Schwalbova, Margita; Katarina Hradska, editor. Zila som Zivoty Druhych (Zo spomienok lekarky na Osviencim), 2001 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Gilovci, Levi a Chana. Osudy jednej rodiny, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Pajak, Henryk. Jedwabne Geszefty, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Photocopies from historical works on Jedwabne, Circa 1981-1993 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- E-mail from listservs and articles relating to Jedwabne, printouts, 1996-2001 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
- Materials related to 60th anniversary commemoration on July 10, 2001, of the massacre of Jedwabne's Jews (Box 1, Folder 12-17)
  Includes invitation, clippings, and ceremony program.
- List of former inhabitants of Jedwabne, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 18)